Finding Aid for James H. Cissel papers, 1934-1943
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James H. Cissel papers 1934-1943
Cissel, James H., 1889-1949.
1.0 linear foot.
85962 Aa 2
Professor of Civil Engineering at the University of Michigan; designer of the proposed Mackinac Bridge; and member of the Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, blueprints and notes concerning the design and construction of the Mackinac Bridge in Michigan. Correspondents include: Mortimer E. Cooley and G. Donald Kennedy.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 1884 ) was transferred from the University of Michigan College of Engineering.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
James Harlan Cissel, born in Goodland, Kansas, June 24, 1889, was Professor of Civil Engineering at the University of Michigan for thirty-three years. A 1910 graduate of Purdue University, Professor Cissel spent five years in the engineering departments of several railroad companies before joining the faculty of the University of Michigan in 1915.
From 1933 to 1936, Cissel worked with the Michigan State Highway Department as engineer in charge of bridge design. In 1934, the state established the Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority and Professor Cissel joined the agency as Consulting Engineer. In 1941, under the administration of Governor Murray D. Van Wagoner, a 4200 ft. causeway for a proposed bridge was completed stretching south into the Straits from St. Ignace. World War II temporarily stalled the effort to build a bridge across the straits of Mackinac, however, and even after the war, there was a delay in revitalizing the bridge movement. In 1950, the Mackinac Bridge Authority, which had been dissolved in 1947, was re-established. The Mackinac Bridge was built and opened to traffic on November 1, 1957 along the route Professor Cissel had originally recommended twenty years before.
A designer of many bridges, Professor Cissel was recognized as a teacher and technical consultant in the field of structural engineering. He died on January 29, 1949 at the age of fifty-nine.
The James H. Cissel Papers, 1934-1943, contain approximately one linear ft. of materials and serve as an interesting account of the architecture and technology of bridge design in the 1930s and document a little known period in the history of the Mackinac Bridge. The papers are comprised of materials pertaining to Cissel's involvement with the design and construction of the proposed Mackinac Straits Bridge. The collection consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings, architectural and design studies, and blueprints. The original order of the collection has for the most part been maintained. Series in the collection include: Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings, Ferry Boat Data, Legislation, Mackinac Straits Bridge Project, Publications, and Blueprints.
Subjects:
Cissel, James H. (James Harlan), b. 1889.; Bridges--Michigan.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Michigan. Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority.; Traffic engineering--Michigan.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ferries.; Mackinac, Straits of (Mich.); Mackinaw City (Mich.)
Contributors:
Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Kennedy, G. Donald (George Donald), 1900-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence file is arranged chronologically, 1934-1940, and includes such correspondents as George E. Bishop, Mortimer E. Cooley, and G. Donald Kennedy.
  - 1934-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937 (Box 1)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings
  The Newspaper Clippings delineate the progress of the proposed Mackinac Straits Bridge during the years of 1934 to 1940. In addition to coverage of the legislation relating to the bridge, the clippings also include editorials.
  - 1934-1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1937 (Box 1)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
- Ferry Boat Data, 1923-1943
  The Ferry Boat Data series includes photographs, traffic growth charts, receipt summaries, regulations, and newspaper clippings. Highway traffic maps and monthly and yearly charts of vehicles transported by the ferries make up the Traffic Data folder in this series.
  - Ferry Boat Operation Data for the years 1923-1938, (includes photographs) (Box 1)
  - Traffic Data of Michigan State Ferry for the years 1923-1943 (Box 1)
- Legislation, 1934-1939
  The Legislation file includes bills relating to the Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority from 1934 to 1939, proposals, and testimony by the State Highway Department's Murray D. Van Wagoner.
  - Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority (Box 1)
- Mackinac Straits Bridge Project Studies and Reports
  The Mackinac Straits Bridge Project series consists of preliminary studies made by Professor Cissel comparing three proposed routes with accompanying exhibits including soundings, cost estimates, and blueprints. Also included is a comparative cost study developed by Glenn A. Alt and A. A. Jakkula of alternate route/design studies and the 1940 report prepared by Modjeski and Masters, consulting engineers.
  - Comparative Studies of Cost for Three Proposed Routes (with exhibits), 1934, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "A Report Showing the Comparative Costs of Three Routes Crossing the Straits of Mackinac" by Glenn L. Alt and A.A. Jakkula, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Studies for alternate routes and designs, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Report of Modjeski and Masters, consulting engineers, on Mackinac Straits Bridge (Box 1)
- Publications, 1935-1939
  Publications, consisting mainly of magazine articles and theses, further document the effort to build a bridge and span from 1935 to 1939 with a large portion of the materials authored by Cissel.
  - Magazine articles and theses regarding effort to build bridge (Box 1)
- Blueprints, 1934-1935, 1938-1939
  Blueprints show the three different routes considered for the Mackinac Bridge as well as location studies for foundations and borings.
  - Proposed Bridge over Straits of Mackinac (Box 1)
  - Location Studies
    - Borings and Foundations (Box 1)
    - Proposed Bridge over Straits of Mackinac (Box 1)